<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>andrewbelfield.com</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>commonplace book</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“What is happening? Today there is a great silence over the earth, a great silence, and stillness, a great silence because the King sleeps; the earth was in terror and was still, because God slept in the flesh and raised up those who were sleeping from the ages. God has died in the flesh, and the underworld has trembled.”&lt;br /&gt;
—from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vatican.va/spirit/documents/spirit_20010414_omelia-sabato-santo_en.html&quot;&gt;an ancient homily for Holy Saturday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“O truly blessed night,&lt;br /&gt;
worthy alone to know the time and hour&lt;br /&gt;
when Christ rose from the underworld!”&lt;br /&gt;
–from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usccb.org/prayer-and-worship/liturgical-year-and-calendar/easter/easter-proclamation-exsultet&quot;&gt;Easter Exultet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But the harvest has been dark: the forms of our best rebellious art have become mere gestures, shticks, not only sterile but perversely enslaving. How can, even the idea of rebellion against corporate culture stay meaningful when Chrysler Inc. advertises trucks by invoking ‘The Dodge Rebellion’? How is one to be a bona fide iconoclast when Burger King sells onion rings with ‘Sometimes You Gotta Break the Rules’?”&lt;br /&gt;
—David Foster Wallace&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For teaching always &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; feel somewhat false, somewhat incomplete. In the classroom, I take things I love and adapt them. I abridge them. I simplify. I commit the heresy of paraphrase. I make comparisons and explanatory analogies at which specialists would wince. I make reading lists, which always leave somebody important out—whether I cut Thoreau to make room for Harriet Jacobs (a stunningly vivid and economical writer) or the other way around. I find the right level of oversimplification for my audience, I go directly to it, and then, by degrees, I retreat from it, inviting students to follow me into greater complexity.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Philip Christman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For he took the ancientness [of our nature] in order to infuse his newness in us. He took a single ancientness, that is, the one of punishment, in order to destroy our twofold one, that is, of punishment and of fault.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Peter Lombard (trans. Giulio Silano)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Education has to be first of all a matter of opening a person to the possibility of love.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Herbert McCabe, OP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Death and resurrection do not destroy the work of incarnation; they consummate it. They do not go back over it, effecting a disincarnation; they lead toward the goal, by spiritualizing even the flesh. Thus a spiritual Christianity, a Christianity which puts the sign of the cross on everything and which accepts no human value without taking care to transform it, is not a disincarnated Christianity; it is the only authentic Christianity, the only one in which the ‘incarnation’ is not a snare.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Henri de Lubac, SJ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The central doctrine of Christianity, then, is not that God is a bastard. It is, in the words of the late Dominican theologian Herbert McCabe, that if you don’t love you’re dead, and if you do, they’ll kill you. Here, then, is your pie in the sky and opium of the people.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Terry Eagleton, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v28/n20/terry-eagleton/lunging-flailing-mispunching&quot;&gt;on new atheist misconceptions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Theology is a contemplative discourse that is defined by its attempt to understand this goodness as well as it can be understood, and to arrive at a notion of justice that flows from it. The language appropriate to theology, according to Gutierrez, is the union of the contemplative and prophetic, of the contemplation of God’s love and the ‘overturning’ it implies in its very mode of revelation.”&lt;br /&gt;
—John Cavadini, on theology and the preferential option for the poor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As a term describing the kind of activity theology does, ‘science’ is better than, e.g., ‘discipline,’ which perhaps sounds more natural to contemporary ears. ‘Discipline’ unavoidably echoes the Weberian iron cage of &lt;em&gt;Wissenschaft als Beruf&lt;/em&gt;, while &lt;em&gt;scientia&lt;/em&gt; is among the standard terms in the Latin West for the kind of cognitive-contemplative intimacy humans may possess with what they come to know.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Paul J. Griffiths&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Truly thrilling thinking is ungainly.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Phil Christman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the three weeks that followed the Braves series and the big bust-out, the Mets won ten games, lost nine, and moved up into eighth place. In this tiny euphoric period, Met followers began to collect and exchange tidings, tidbits, and little moral tales that seemed to confirm the new vigor and startling bourgeois respectability of their old ne’er-do-wells.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Roger Angell, in May 1963&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The sentence ‘How would the Trinity have been the Trinity if God had not created a world, and there had therefore been no creature Jesus to be the Son, or had let the fallen creation go, with the same result?’ is often taken for a real question. And here I do have a retraction to make. In the past I have sometimes responded to the supposed question, saying that God would presumably have somehow been the same triune God that he is, but that we can say nothing further about that ‘somehow’. I now think that even this response concedes too much to our unbaptized notion of time, by supposing that the collection of words quoted at the beginning of this paragraph actually makes a question which one can answer, however sparingly. It has now dawned on me that the putative question is nonsense, and so therefore is my previous attempt to respond to it.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Robert W. Jenson, on the &lt;em&gt;Logos asarkos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Saisi d’horreur, voici de nouveau que j’entends&lt;br /&gt;
L’inexorable appel de la voix merveilleuse. …”&lt;br /&gt;
—Paul Claudel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is no satisfactory explanation of style, no infallible guide to good writing, no assurance that a person who thinks clearly will be able to write clearly, no key that unlocks the door, no inflexible rule by which the young writer may shape his course. He will often find himself steering by stars that are disturbingly in motion.”&lt;br /&gt;
—William Strunk, Jr. &amp;amp; E.B. White&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/reading/2021/04/30/commonplace-book/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/reading/2021/04/30/commonplace-book/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>commonplace book</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Etc. is a sign of the process of thinking and writing. Etc. is a note within a note from the author to himself reminding him of the rest of a thought or an association so evident to him that he does not need to write it out. Etc. in a work released to a reader invites a witness, a closer witness to the process, the act of writing. Etc. invites or demands that the reader complete the thought, the association; etc. says that both writer and reader knows how this continues.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Lydia Davis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I use this term [sc., excommunication] in a rather loose sense as I do not wish to enter into details of canon law.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Herbert McCabe, in a footnote&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Middle English &lt;em&gt;ars&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;ers&lt;/em&gt;, from Old English &lt;em&gt;ærs&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;ears&lt;/em&gt;; akin to Old High German &amp;amp; Old Norse &lt;em&gt;ars&lt;/em&gt; buttocks, Greek &lt;em&gt;orrhos&lt;/em&gt; buttocks, &lt;em&gt;oura&lt;/em&gt; tail”&lt;br /&gt;
—History and Etymology for &lt;em&gt;ass&lt;/em&gt; in Merriam-Webster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To glance through a book is to look for what one knows already.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Maurice Blondel at his soutenance de thèse, upon learning the obscurity of his work caused his examiners to skim its pages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To live in this world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you must be able&lt;br /&gt;
to do three things:&lt;br /&gt;
to love what is mortal;&lt;br /&gt;
to hold it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;against your bones knowing&lt;br /&gt;
your own life depends on it;&lt;br /&gt;
and, when the time comes to let it go&lt;br /&gt;
to let it go.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Mary Oliver&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Est enim dicere divinam essentiam finire creaturas, in quantum ab ipsa sunt ut a principio et in quantum ad ipsam ordinantur ut ad finem et sunt secundum ipsam. Nam, sicut dicit Trismegistus, «divina essentia est sicut sphaera intelligibilis, cuius centrum est ubique, circumferentia vero nusquam».”&lt;br /&gt;
—&lt;em&gt;Summa halensis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To know is primarily and principally to seize and embrace within yourself an &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; who is capable of seizing and embracing you: it is to live by the life of another living being.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Pierre Rousselot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“la luz de la mañana”&lt;br /&gt;
—Barbara Bregstein’s &lt;em&gt;Complete Spanish Step-by-Step&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That morning it was an old hymn in praise of farming. I liked the shape of it on my lips, the soothing lists of plants and crops, of crofts and cotes, herds and flocks, and the stars that wheeled above them.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Madeline Miller&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By his memory, Augustine discovers that his life opens up to reveal Your own; through memory, he meets You the Creator, Sustainer, and Redeemer. He remembers, and he finds himself in the story of Your life with the world.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Natalie Carnes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To tell other people what our lives mean is to draw them deeper into ourselves, and to listen to what someone tells us their life means is to be drawn deeper into the mystery of both their humanity and humanity’s maker. To impose upon another the meaning of their life is, by contrast, a kind of pretense at divinity. It is to tell another person something that only God can tell them, to claim the ultimate interpretive authority over experiences that do not belong to us. In a final sense, it is to do violence to someone else’s humanity and to the very purpose of language, for we have language precisely in order to invite others into our own interiority, to tell them our story.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Daniel Walden, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.commonwealmagazine.org/gender-sex-and-other-nonsense&quot;&gt;on gender and self-narration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It (charity) is as strong as death, nay stronger than death for charity forced even death itself to die in the death of the Redeemer. O insuperable virtue of charity, which indeed conquered the insuperable Himself; and Him to whom all are subject, you in some way subjected to all, when God, overcome by love, humbled Himself, taking the form of a servant, and was made not only a human, but the reproach of humans and the castoff of the people! And if it was strong against God, how much more will it prevail against humans?”&lt;br /&gt;
—Richard of St. Victor, quoted by Pierre Rousselot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; is the unending task of theology in its search for faith, and it is in the Christian experience that it finds its ‘given’.”&lt;br /&gt;
—M. D. Chenu&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For ultimately the choice to abandon speech is a &lt;em&gt;reasoned&lt;/em&gt; choice, and the desire to reason one’s way through life is precisely that—a desire. What God has brought together in the human spirit, no one should attempt to tear asunder.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Roberto J. De La Noval, &lt;a href=&quot;https://churchlifejournal.nd.edu/articles/the-kids-arent-alt-lite/&quot;&gt;on &lt;em&gt;Heroes of the Fourth Turning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s a reason the most visible gothic tradition in American culture comes from the South: a place where history cannot be ignored or escaped. The deformations produced through history, through landscape, through bigotry, through poverty, through even the extremes of the weather—these are the subjects of ‘Southern gothic.’”&lt;br /&gt;
—B. D. McClay, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebaffler.com/latest/american-gothic-mcclay&quot;&gt;on American gothic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The theologian is the person who dares to speak the Word of God in human terms.”&lt;br /&gt;
—M. D. Chenu&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For the unity of this Tradition in all that affects the essentials of Catholicism does not seem to me an empty term, an abstract theological thesis which a careful examination of the facts would invalidate. On the contrary, the greater becomes one’s familiarity with this immense army of witnesses, the closer one’s association with this one or othat, the keener is the realization of how deep is the unity in which all those meet together who, faithful to the one Church, live by the same faith in the same Holy Spirit.”&lt;br /&gt;
—Henri de Lubac&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/reading/2021/03/31/commonplace/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/reading/2021/03/31/commonplace/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>el víacrucis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Holy Week of any year—that week of prayer and fasting ordered to the cross and, eventually, the empty tomb—always has a nearness to the first Holy Week, as the drama of the liturgy moves modern-day Christians through the drama of the passion. Holy Week 2020, however, seemed especially near. The reality of coronavirus was setting in, along with the bitter realization it would be a long time before we could safely gather with family, friends, and religious communities. People all around the world were (and still are) dying, and the coronavirus crisis exacerbated existing injustices in our world: poverty, lack of access to healthcare, racism. It was not hard to imagine the disciples’ despair, their feeling that the world crumbled before them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/el-viacrucis.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;a community celebration of the Sations of the Cross, walking along the main path in Cabaña&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was (and am) fortunate to live in an intentional community, committed to shared living in an interreligious space. It was around this time last year that we began celebrating liturgy together regularly—weekly prayer services, a Passover Seder, and the Easter Triduum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laurel Marshall Potter—colleague, friend, housemate—and I composed the following prayer service for our community. Our community—Jews and Christians, Salvadorans and Americans and Koreans, students and young professionals—gathered on Good Friday 2020 to reflect on the movement of the passion and what it revealed of the suffering of our world. I am grateful to Laurel for permitting me to share this service on this site; I am grateful, too, to our community for affording us a space for prayer and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opening-prayer&quot;&gt;opening prayer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way of the cross is an apocalyptic event in that it is a revelatory event. The cross reveals the injustices of our world, the manner in which those in power gain and keep power, the complicity each of us has in communal sin. Yet it reveals too the depths of God’s love. It is not God’s will that this injustice persist; it is not God’s will that the powerful remain so; it is not God’s will that the guilt of sin stains us forever. Jesus’s long walk to Golgotha makes manifest to us who God is: the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, the God of the prophets, the God of the living, the God of mercy and justice. This God walks the way of death in solidarity with all who suffer, as one who suffers, that they might suffer no more. The way ends on the cross in death—and by that very death, so ends death itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-first-station-jesus-is-condemned-to-death&quot;&gt;the first station. Jesus is condemned to death&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus has exposed what the poorest and most vulnerable among us have long known—ours is a culture of death. Eager for profits, for consumer goods, for power, our culture readily sacrifices its poor, its elderly, its vulnerable to the market. Jesus, like many today, is a victim of this culture: as religious authorities and the crowd looked on, he was condemned to death lest empire lose its grip on its colonial possession. Pilate thought he could exempt himself from this culture of death; he thought he could wash his hands of the violence. Little did he know his complicity in death is his responsibility for death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-second-station-jesus-carries-his-cross&quot;&gt;the second station. Jesus carries his cross.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor and marginalized disproportionately carry the burden of the culture of death. Black and brown bodies, women, queer people, people who are immunocompromised, ill and disabled, prisoners, the elderly, and the abused all bear the weight of structures that uphold kingdoms of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-third-station-jesus-falls-for-the-first-time&quot;&gt;the third station. Jesus falls for the first time.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the weight of the cross, that symbol of death’s reign, Jesus stumbles. His stumble is that of the economic poor, then and now—those who subsist on inadequate wages, who do not have access to affordable healthcare or housing or proper nourishment. The weight is unbearable; he is brought to his knees, and not for the last time. His journey is only just beginning—how, under the weight of poverty and homelessness and material instability, can it be borne?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fourth-station-jesus-meets-his-mother-mary&quot;&gt;the fourth station. Jesus meets his mother, Mary.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How acute Mary’s own pain when she sees the suffering of her child! When we love our family, chosen and given, we open ourselves up the pain of their suffering. Our relationships make us vulnerable, and they also make us human. Mary is not absent from Jesus’s crucifixion, even though it is painful, hopeless, maddening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fifth-station-simon-of-cyrene-helps-jesus-carry-his-cross&quot;&gt;the fifth station. Simon of Cyrene helps Jesus carry his cross&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/alfombra.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;an alfombra in Guatemala&quot; class=&quot;img-left&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Cuando el pobre crea en la pobre&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ya podremos cantar libertad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cuando la/el pobre crea en el/la pobre,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Construiremos la fraternidad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuando el pobre busca al pobre&lt;br /&gt;
y nace la organización&lt;br /&gt;
es que empieza nuestra liberación.&lt;br /&gt;
Cuando el pobre anuncia al pobre&lt;br /&gt;
la esperanza que Él nos dio,&lt;br /&gt;
Ya su Reino entre nosotros nació.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sixth-station-veronica-wipes-the-face-of-jesus&quot;&gt;the sixth station. Veronica wipes the face of Jesus.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kind gestures are not worthless. Though much more is needed to interrupt the crucifixions that surround us, we cannot deem small kindnesses unimportant. Veronica knows she cannot stop the parade of death, but she risks drawing near to Jesus to offer a fleeting moment of relief. Immediate, compassionate relief must be part of our response to the culture of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-seventh-station-jesus-falls-for-the-second-time&quot;&gt;the seventh station. Jesus falls for the second time.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, death’s weight is too much—Jesus falls. He fears for himself, certainly, but he fears for his family, his disciples, his people. Jesus is not free of the anxiety of death; neither are we. Especially in times of uncertainty as our physical health is at risk, so too is our mental health. Worry, anxiety, fear, depression—these and other demons torment us. When we are responsible for the well-being of others, our mental health is only further strained. We feel we can hardly bear it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-eighth-station-jesus-meets-the-women-of-jerusalem&quot;&gt;the eighth station. Jesus meets the women of Jerusalem.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerusalem was weak compared to Rome, but strong compared to Nazareth. These privileged women, residents of a politically strategic city, express culturally sanctioned horror and pity for the poor radical from backwater Galilee. They play their role in the drama of Roman crucifixions. Jesus says to them, “Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for me, but weep for yourselves and for your children.” Their sense of security is an illusion, and their false pity is damning. We are all both complicit and dehumanized by the culture of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ninth-station-jesus-falls-for-the-third-time&quot;&gt;the ninth station. Jesus falls for the third time.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in moments of physical and mental strength, we are not immune to social isolation and spiritual desolation. Jesus’s third fall is perhaps the most crushing: it is in this moment that he realizes how alone he is. He has found small comforts along the way—the tears of his mother, the strength of Simon, the cloth of Veronica—but from here on out he is desperately alone. Our culture of death is a culture of isolation, for everyone dies alone. In that isolation is a spiritual desolation; apart from the fabric of our society, what meaning can our lives have? The isolation of coronavirus is a symptom of a deeper sickness: a culture that does not allow us community and solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tenth-station-jesus-is-stripped-of-his-clothes&quot;&gt;the tenth station. Jesus is stripped of his clothes.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“First they came for the socialists, and I did not speak out—&lt;br /&gt;
Because I was not a socialist.&lt;br /&gt;
Then they came for the trade unionists, and I did not speak out—&lt;br /&gt;
Because I was not a trade unionist.&lt;br /&gt;
Then they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out—&lt;br /&gt;
Because I was not a Jew.&lt;br /&gt;
Then they came for me—&lt;br /&gt;
and there was no one left to speak for me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having robbed us of our solidarity, the culture of death, when it comes for us, strips us of all pretense of security, of control, and of belonging. We fear the day that our illusion of invincibility is stripped from us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-eleventh-station-jesus-is-nailed-to-the-cross&quot;&gt;the eleventh station. Jesus is nailed to the cross.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nails by which Jesus is fixed to the cross is the physical pain and torture by which empire keeps its power. Jesus was a discontent, a threat, a rabble rouser—he was a problem that required a “just” solution. Crucifixion—state-sanctioned violence—is that “justice,” a demonic perversion of God’s true justice. Jesus cries out as the nails pierce his flesh, but the soldiers care not; he gasps for breath as the cross is lifted up, but the crowd jeers still. Empire has power; empire keeps power. It is the way of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-twelfth-station-jesus-dies-on-the-cross&quot;&gt;the twelfth station. Jesus dies on the cross.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My God, my God, why have you forsaken me? Why are you so far from saving me, so far from my cries of anguish?” The Gospel writers cite the psalmist in the moment of Jesus’s death on the cross, and claim that Jesus really does die—he goes to the place of the dead. He dies torn between belief in a God who has promised life and the reality of his own death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-thirteenth-station-jesus-is-taken-down-from-the-cross&quot;&gt;the thirteenth station. Jesus is taken down from the cross.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all this, the long walk from Pilate’s court to Golgotha, the end is almost anticlimactic. Jesus dies, not without a shout, but he dies nonetheless. What remains verges on mundane—he must be removed from the cross, arrangements must be made, a funeral must be planned. There will be time enough to grieve later; for now, there are things to be done. There is a numbness; someone who was once a fixture of our lives is now gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fourteenth-station-jesus-is-placed-in-the-tomb&quot;&gt;the fourteenth station. Jesus is placed in the tomb.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember one time at a funeral in Santa Tecla: a family stood around their grandmother’s grave as the gravediggers began to shovel dirt on top of her lowered coffin. As the dirt fell and hit the bottom, the thud was the only sound we could hear. The finality of the dirt on the coffin was the only real thing in the world. It was a final goodbye. The disciples must have felt this same kind of grief at the finality of Jesus’s death and the end of what they thought was the call of their lives.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V. El sacrificio verdadero es un corazón penitente.&lt;br /&gt;
℟. Dios, tú no despreciarás un corazón penitente y roto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-prayer&quot;&gt;closing prayer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disciples were sure it was over. Even if Jesus’s voice echoed in their heads, it was just that—an echo. There was little else they could do but return to their fishing nets and try to carry on with some semblance of a normal life. Even though Jesus defied their expectations in life, still they could not imagine a reality beyond death. That’s what death meant. It was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the disciples could not imagine a future for Jesus beyond his death, neither can we imagine a future beyond the cultures of death that constrain our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/el-rosario.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;the fifteenth station in Iglesia El Rosario in San Salvador&quot; class=&quot;img-right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking this way of the cross with Jesus, we see the pervasiveness of this death culture. We have seen the seemingly insurmountable power of injustice, and we have witnessed our own complicity in that injustice. It seems foolish to hope that it could be otherwise, that we could be freed of the structures of sin that constrain our freedom and flourishing, that the systems of injustice could be dismantled. Who will beat the guns into plowshares when there are wars to be fought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet this is our hope. This is what God has promised, again and again in the Law and in the Prophets and in the Gospels. We know not when or how, but we do know this—God always finds the unlooked-for solution. God always creates new realities and paradigms beyond our imaginative capacities to be in relationship with us. This is our hope, foolish though it may seem, that God will do good on God’s promise. On this darkest of days, out of the very depths of despair, we can but cry our foolish hope: “Hosanna, hosanna in the highest.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;℟. Glory be to God, now and forever. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This story is Laurel’s. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/theology/2021/03/29/el-viacrucis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/theology/2021/03/29/el-viacrucis/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>a christmas tree blessing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Good and gracious God,&lt;br /&gt;
you who are power and wisdom and goodness—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bless this tree,&lt;br /&gt;
a sign of life and freshness and perseverance in our midst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May it stand as a reminder&lt;br /&gt;
of light in the dark of night,&lt;br /&gt;
and of life in the dead of winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May its supple branches and sharp, sweet scent&lt;br /&gt;
keep fresh in our minds and our hands&lt;br /&gt;
the mercy and generosity you show&lt;br /&gt;
in all your dealings with your beloved people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May its evergreen boughs,&lt;br /&gt;
untouched by the chill of snow and frost,&lt;br /&gt;
embolden us in our commitment to love and largesse,&lt;br /&gt;
as we too refuse the chill of consumerism and greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bless the land that provided this tree,&lt;br /&gt;
and bless the land that now holds up our home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May we remember the bounty of the land&lt;br /&gt;
as we seek to make ourselves native to it&lt;br /&gt;
and to honor its past, present, and future inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have nothing that we did not first receive;&lt;br /&gt;
we give nothing except what we have received.&lt;br /&gt;
Bless us with your presence as we prepare, during this Advent season,&lt;br /&gt;
to receive what you have to give,&lt;br /&gt;
and give what we have been given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/theology/2020/11/29/a-christmas-tree-blessing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/theology/2020/11/29/a-christmas-tree-blessing/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>of baptism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear C—,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday, on a cool and bright New York day with the edges of autumn just beginning to creep into the last days of summer, you were baptized. Like autumn into summer, you may find the fact of your baptism—something in which you had no say and of which you have no memory—creeping into your life in strange and unexpected ways; you may not know quite why you were baptized; you may wonder what the point of your baptism was at all. I write this note in the hope it can offer some guidance here. Given the subject matter, this note is woefully short (despite its length!), but I hope it’s helpful even still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The joys of life are many, and you’ll come to learn these in time—riding a bike without training wheels, enjoying a meal you helped to prepare, reading a book your mom loved when she was your age. But when you have enjoyed all life has to offer and when you come to the end of your time on earth, there life’s final obligation imposes itself. If you’ll allow me to be blunt: all living things—human beings, animals, plants—must die. Even nonliving things tend toward decay—given enough time, rocks break down into sand, stars explode into stardust, houses fall apart. This is an unfortunate, tragic, unsettling fact, but a fact nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is exactly because of this burden of death that your parents had you baptized. Baptism, you see, is a remedy to the death into which all living things are born. When you were baptized, water was poured over your head three times. This ritual symbolically—though as Catholics we really ought to say “sacramentally”—puts the person being baptized to death; when she is lifted out of the baptismal font, she is raised to new life and made a member of the community founded by Christ and made up of all the baptized. This community—which we call “the church”—is freed by baptism from the reign of death and liberated into a reign of life. The freedom of the Christian is a freedom to live in and by the love of God—a love that is totally selfless and pure, concerned never for itself but always for the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just as being born naturally imposed upon you an obligation of death, so does being reborn sacramentally impose upon you an obligation. And as you would expect, the obligation baptism imposes is exactly the opposite of the one imposed by being born: the baptized are obliged to live!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christians have a peculiar understanding of what it is to live; peculiar, at least, according to how the rest of the world tends to think of what it is to live. For Christians to live, they must live for others—they must feed the hungry, clothe the naked, take in the stranger, visit the imprisoned. (For more on this, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matthew+25%3A31-46&amp;amp;version=RSVCE&quot;&gt;chapter 25 of Matthew’s Gospel&lt;/a&gt;; or the Sermon on the Mount, found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=matthew+5-7&amp;amp;version=RSVCE&quot;&gt;chapters 5–7 of the same Gospel&lt;/a&gt;.) And very often, Christians must inconvenience themselves to live in this way—they must feed the hungry with their own food, clothe the naked with their own clothing, take the stranger into their own home, and visit the imprisoned on their own time. (St. Basil the Great says the unworn jacket in your closet rightfully belongs to the poor person who has no jacket!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) In this way, the life you received in your baptism is not so much yours as it is others’, especially those most in need of your help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obligation to live liberates us from the relentless rhythm of decay, that dirge of death according to which the rest of the world marches. Yet that baptismal obligation is not always pleasant—as I’ve just suggested, it involves a personal cost to the Christian. You may find yourself with less food than you might otherwise have because you’ve given some to your hungry neighbor, for example. What’s more, you may find the task itself unpleasant. The hungry might lack table manners, or the poor decorum; the stranger’s unusual customs might confuse you, and the prisoner’s past might frighten. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Vincent_de_Paul&quot;&gt;St. Vincent de Paul has some really lovely words on this&lt;/a&gt;; I remain forever haunted by his claim: “It is only for your love alone that the poor will forgive you the bread you give to them.” I have tears in my eyes as I recall my own failings in this respect.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another reason why we might shy away from baptism’s obligation (and many, regrettably, do). The obligation of baptism to live runs directly contrary to the world and its designs. Unlike the white garment of life that the baptized wear, the world wears a death shroud and, wittingly or not, the world seeks to shroud more of the living in death. There’s a reason, after all, that there are people without enough food, or too poor for clothing or a home, or lacking the freedom you enjoy. For the Christian to live her life for others, then, and for her to spread life in a world of death, is a subversive, even dangerous, undertaking. Indeed, the Christian seeks nothing less than liberation for all those bound by chains of death: liberation from hunger and poverty, and, yes, from the literal chains of the prison yard. The Christian seeks to undo, once and for all, the pattern of death in the world. (For more on this, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=luke+1%3A47-55&amp;amp;version=RSVCE&quot;&gt;Mary’s Magnificat toward the end of the first chapter of the Gospel of Luke&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sort of subversive, dangerous trouble Jesus got himself into. He came into a world of death preaching a message of life and love; he rejected the status quo and sought to undo the patterns of death that keep all, oppressors and oppressed alike, in chains. But the powers that be would not stand for it; they dealt with the problem in the only way they knew how, and they had him killed. Ironically, it was this very act of violence against life that assured the final victory of life over death (but that’s another email for another time; in the meantime, you might take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+cor+15%3A35-58&amp;amp;version=RSVCE&quot;&gt;chapter 15 of Paul’s First Letter to the Corinthians, especially verses 35 and following&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The life that your baptism demands of you is subversive: for this reason, the world may try to stop you, as it did Jesus. There will be some who take advantage of your generosity; there will be some who ridicule you for what they take to be foolishness on your part; there may even be some who commit acts of violence against you, so desperate will they be to stop the liberation you bring. I hope this is not the case for you; but I also hope that you take the demands of your baptism seriously, and that you live the life you have been freed to live. St. Irenaeus, one of the first theologians in the church’s history, said that the glory of God is the human being fully alive. I hope you glorify God in all that you do by rejecting death and choosing to be fully alive for the liberation of yourself and of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you find yourself inspired by the liberating power of your baptism; perhaps you find yourself daunted at the prospect of such a demanding life; perhaps you find yourself vaguely annoyed at having spent so much time reading all this nonsense! (I hope it’s not that last one, but I’m aware it’s at least a possibility.) However you respond to this—whether positively, negatively, or even indifferently—I hope you know there are people in your life who will always be available to talk to you about this. Your mom and dad rightly saw the good of baptism and so decided it was for you; your aunt V— and uncle B— as your godparents, have a special responsibility to guide you in matters of faith and spirituality; and I hope you’ll think of me as someone you can talk to about this. I promise you’ll always find in these people generous listeners, patient conversation partners, and loving family members. I look forward to the day we can talk about some of this, but until then I remain—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;your uncle by law and your brother in Christ,&lt;br /&gt;
Drew&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I wrote this note for my niece on the occassion of her baptism. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In his homily &lt;em&gt;I Will Tear Down My Barns&lt;/em&gt;: “When someone steals another’s clothes, we call them a thief. Should we not give the same name to one who could clothe the naked and does not? The bread in your cupboard belongs to the hungry; the coat unused in your closet belongs to the one who needs it; the shoes rotting in your closet belong to the one who has no shoes; the money which you hoard up belongs to the poor.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/theology/2020/09/22/of-baptism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/theology/2020/09/22/of-baptism/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>that attention is love</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wedding-hands.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;wedding-hands&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the very year of our engagement, &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt; was released.&lt;br /&gt;
Toward the end of this magnanimous film&lt;br /&gt;
the titular character meets with her English teacher, Sister Sarah Joan,&lt;br /&gt;
to discuss a short story she wrote for class.&lt;br /&gt;
That wise nun comments how clearly&lt;br /&gt;
Lady Bird’s love for Sacramento comes through,&lt;br /&gt;
much to Lady Bird’s — and the viewer’s— surprise.&lt;br /&gt;
Up till now we have seen Lady Bird straining&lt;br /&gt;
at the borders of her hometown&lt;br /&gt;
and dreaming of going to college&lt;br /&gt;
where there is, as she puts it, “culture”—&lt;br /&gt;
somewhere like New York City,&lt;br /&gt;
or at least, she says naively, Connecticut.&lt;br /&gt;
Unwilling to call what she feels for Sacramento love,&lt;br /&gt;
Lady Bird demurs, saying,&lt;br /&gt;
“I guess I pay attention.”
Sister Sarah Joan, sage-like, responds,&lt;br /&gt;
“Don’t you think maybe they are the same thing?&lt;br /&gt;
Love and attention?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacqueline,&lt;br /&gt;
whom I now have the great and singular joy to call my wife,&lt;br /&gt;
is someone who pays attention.&lt;br /&gt;
How else to explain her acute focus,&lt;br /&gt;
an enviable ability to block out all distractions and interruptions?&lt;br /&gt;
How else to explain her fascination with&lt;br /&gt;
and appreciation for art in all its forms,&lt;br /&gt;
her own deeply-felt artistic expression in song and in dance?&lt;br /&gt;
Indeed it is by this very attention&lt;br /&gt;
that Jacqueline sees the world insightfully and perceptively,&lt;br /&gt;
that she recognizes with clarity the virtues and vices and motivations&lt;br /&gt;
of those whom she encounters in life and in literature.&lt;br /&gt;
I recall our earliest conversations at St. Bonaventure,&lt;br /&gt;
where we sat in Hickey Dining Hall&lt;br /&gt;
long after our plates had been emptied and our stomachs filled,&lt;br /&gt;
as we canvassed literature, film, television, and, most of all, music.&lt;br /&gt;
Though I did not realize it at the time,&lt;br /&gt;
what drew me to her,&lt;br /&gt;
besides her evident beauty—&lt;br /&gt;
and the prospect of dating a third-generation SBU legacy—&lt;br /&gt;
was her keen sense of the world, borne out of a piercing eye.&lt;br /&gt;
It was breathtaking,&lt;br /&gt;
enlightening,&lt;br /&gt;
challenging,&lt;br /&gt;
delighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what can only be called a miracle of divine grace,&lt;br /&gt;
Jacqueline has turned her attentive gaze to me.&lt;br /&gt;
To be beheld by Jacqueline is thrilling.&lt;br /&gt;
She is a source of comfort,&lt;br /&gt;
sharing in my hopes and joys, my griefs and anxieties.&lt;br /&gt;
She provides refuge from the lonely, isolating, solitary world I inhabit&lt;br /&gt;
of dusty books and long-forgotten names.&lt;br /&gt;
Under her eyes, I am not anonymous;&lt;br /&gt;
I am seen.&lt;br /&gt;
But to be beheld by Jacqueline can be frightening indeed.&lt;br /&gt;
Jacqueline sees right through all my pretenses,&lt;br /&gt;
through the false self by which I delude&lt;br /&gt;
(or attempt to delude)&lt;br /&gt;
the world and myself.&lt;br /&gt;
She knows when I complain about my colleagues&lt;br /&gt;
I really give voice to my own insecurities.&lt;br /&gt;
She knows my impatience with others&lt;br /&gt;
only masks my own frustration with myself.&lt;br /&gt;
I cannot but read myself into&lt;br /&gt;
the lover of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Song+of+Songs+2%3A8-10%2C+14%2C+16a%3B+8%3A6-7a&amp;amp;version=NABRE&quot;&gt;Song of Songs&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;br /&gt;
in the eyes of his beloved, he delights:&lt;br /&gt;
“How beautiful you are, my love, how beautiful!&lt;br /&gt;
Your eyes are doves!” (1:15).&lt;br /&gt;
But from those very eyes, he shrinks:&lt;br /&gt;
“Turn your eyes away from me, for they disturb me” (6:5).&lt;br /&gt;
Jacqueline sees me, and so I delight.&lt;br /&gt;
Yet it is precisely because she sees me that I cower,&lt;br /&gt;
for she misses nothing—&lt;br /&gt;
not my shame, nor my sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacqueline,&lt;br /&gt;
in other words,&lt;br /&gt;
sees me not only as I am now—&lt;br /&gt;
sinful indeed and a poor excuse for a Christian—&lt;br /&gt;
but also as I could be; rather, as I should be.&lt;br /&gt;
Her probing stare exhorts me to be who I am created to be—&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew+5%3A1-12a&amp;amp;version=NABRE&quot;&gt;poor in spirit and meek&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;br /&gt;
hungering and thirsting for justice,&lt;br /&gt;
clean of heart and peacemaking.&lt;br /&gt;
Sometimes she does this outright,&lt;br /&gt;
gently and charitably chiding me when I deserve it—&lt;br /&gt;
but most times it is her modeling of Christian discipleship,&lt;br /&gt;
her lived embodiment of those beatitudes&lt;br /&gt;
that points me away from sin and darkness&lt;br /&gt;
and toward righteousness and light.&lt;br /&gt;
Saint Francis of Assisi is attributed as saying,&lt;br /&gt;
“Preach the Gospel always;&lt;br /&gt;
when necessary, use words.”&lt;br /&gt;
Though he surely uttered no such thing,&lt;br /&gt;
Jacqueline lives that proverb ceaselessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indulge me still further.&lt;br /&gt;
Marriage,&lt;br /&gt;
as a sacrament in the Catholic sense,&lt;br /&gt;
is shaped and normed by the cross.&lt;br /&gt;
In all sacraments, no less marriage,&lt;br /&gt;
we die on the cross with Christ,&lt;br /&gt;
and with him leave behind an empty tomb.&lt;br /&gt;
In our sacramental dying and rising&lt;br /&gt;
is anticipated our physical dying and rising.&lt;br /&gt;
Every time a sinner submits to baptism’s watery grave,&lt;br /&gt;
every time the one bloody sacrifice is celebrated&lt;br /&gt;
with the unbloody words &lt;em&gt;hoc est corpus meum&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;br /&gt;
every time two persons die to their selves&lt;br /&gt;
and consent to the union in which they rise together as one,&lt;br /&gt;
Death’s claim over us is broken.&lt;br /&gt;
This is God’s wisdom, foolishness to the world,&lt;br /&gt;
that by Death itself God should bring life.&lt;br /&gt;
Rightly does the Apostle Paul—and do we—&lt;br /&gt;
rejoice with words mocking:&lt;br /&gt;
“Where, O Death, is your sting?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put otherwise,&lt;br /&gt;
the process of dying and rising in the sacraments&lt;br /&gt;
is nothing other than the process of entering into eternal life,&lt;br /&gt;
wherein the last enemy Death finally is defeated.&lt;br /&gt;
To be married in this life is to be made ready&lt;br /&gt;
for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=revelation+19&amp;amp;version=NABRE&quot;&gt;the wedding-feast in the life to come&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;br /&gt;
where we all shall be wedded to the Lamb whose victory the cross is.&lt;br /&gt;
In my marital, sacramental life with Jacqueline,&lt;br /&gt;
and under the clear, precise, charitable, demanding gaze&lt;br /&gt;
by which Jacqueline attends to me,&lt;br /&gt;
I work out the salvation Christ has wrought.&lt;br /&gt;
I am not saved except for her love,&lt;br /&gt;
that is to say her &lt;em&gt;attention&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;br /&gt;
a love and attention that reform me&lt;br /&gt;
not in in her image or in mine,&lt;br /&gt;
but in the image of the LORD.&lt;br /&gt;
This is God’s providential plan for me;&lt;br /&gt;
these are the means by which God,&lt;br /&gt;
in His mercy,&lt;br /&gt;
has ordained that I shall be saved.&lt;br /&gt;
It could not be otherwise.&lt;br /&gt;
Without Jacqueline I turn my face from His face,&lt;br /&gt;
to my own peril;&lt;br /&gt;
with her, I shall look upon the face of the LORD as a friend,&lt;br /&gt;
in life eternal.&lt;br /&gt;
I know not why God has entrusted her to my care—&lt;br /&gt;
for I, as Jacqueline’s spouse, must do the same for her—&lt;br /&gt;
but thanks be that God has seen fit to entrust me to hers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 16:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/theology/2019/05/18/that-attention-is-love/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/theology/2019/05/18/that-attention-is-love/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
